Guide to the Angela Mackail Thirkell Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Angela Mackail Thirkell collection
1947-1960
GEN MSS 283
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.42
(4 boxes)
Collection contains: holograph manuscript drafts of Thirkell's novels Private Enterprise and What Did it Mean?; correspondence between Thirkell and James Tinkham Babb, Barbara Waite Davidson, Gordon and Mary Haight, and others; third-party correspondence by Lance Thirkell, Laura Roberts Collins, C. A. Lejuene, and others; and clippings and printed ephemera relating to Thirkell and her work.
Thirkell, Angela, 1890-1961
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Angela Mackail Thirkell, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection. Materials have been arranged into four series: Gift of Angela Mackail Thirkell, Gift of Gordon Haight, Gift of Margaret Bradley Babb, and Gift of the Angela Thirkell Society.
Authors, English -- 20th Century -- Archives; English literature -- 20th Century; Babb, James T. (James Tinkham), 1899-1968; Collins, Laura Roberts; Davidson, Barbara Waite; Haight, Gordon Sherman; Haight, Mary; Lejeune, C. A. (Caroline Alice), 1897-1973; Thirkell, Angela, 1890-1961; Thirkell, Lance
- Gift of Angela Thirkell, Series I
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Angela Thirkell, 1950, 1955.
  - Private Enterprise, autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1-9)
    Scope and Contents
    Written in pencil in eleven notebooks
  - Thirkell, Angela Mackail. TLS to Gordon S. Haight. London, 1950 Sep 4 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Removed from Private Enterprise, autograph manuscript
  - What Did It Mean?, autograph manuscript, 1953-54 (Box 2, Folder 11-20)
    Written in pencil in 10 notebooks
- Gift of Gordon Haight, Series II
  Gift of Gordon S. Haight, 1984.
  - Babb, James Tinkham. 2 TLS (carbons) to Angela Thirkell, New Haven, 1950-55 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Haight, Gordon Sherman. TL (carbon) to George Sherburn, New Haven, 1948 Nov 8 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    On the same leaf: Haight, Gordon Sherman. TL (carbon) to Willard Thorpe. New Haven, 1948 Nov 8
  - Haight, Gordon Sherman. 33 TL (carbons) to Angela Thirkell, 1947-60 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Kunkel, Beverly W. ALS to Gordon S. Haight, Easton, PA, 1960 May 10 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Sherburn, George. TLS to Gordon S. Haight, Cambridge, Mass., 1948 Nov 14 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Thirkell, Angela. 41 ALS, 7 APCS, 5 ACS, 34 TLS (some with manuscript notes), and 2 TL to Gordon and Mary Haight, 1947-60 (Box 3, Folder 26-28)
    With clippings, business and change of address cards, etc. (6 items)
  - [Thirkell], Lance. ALS to Gordon S. Haight, London, 1955 Mar 5 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Whitney, J. B. TLS (with manuscript note) to Gordon S. Haight. Cambridge, Mass., 1948 Nov 15 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - 3 printed invitations and 1 business card (some with manuscript notes) (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Gift of Margaret Bradley Babb, Series III
  Gift of Margaret Bradley Babb, 1962.
  - Thirkell, Angela. TLS to Mrs. Babb, London, 1955 July 26 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    With calling card
- Gift of Angela Thirkell Society, Series IV
  Gift of Angela Thirkell Society, 2009.
  - Correspondence between Angela Thirkell and Barbara Waite Davidson, 1951-1960, undated (Box 4, Folder 33-36)
  - Letters from Angela Thirkell to Mary Lois Mamer, 1947-1952 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Copies of letters from Angela Thirkell to others, undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence between Lance Thirkell and Laura Roberts Collins, 1983-1986, undated (Box 4, Folder 39-40)
  - Letters from Lance Thirkell to Phyllis Croghan, 1985-1988 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    Includes photograph of Angela Thirkell
  - Correspondence between Lance Thirkell and Barbara Waite Davidson, 1961-1978, undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence between C. A. Lejeune and Barbara Waite Davidson, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Laura Roberts Collins publications correspondence, 1991-194, undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Other third-party correspondence, 1949-2002 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Clippings, 1944-2000, undated (Box 4, Folder 46-48)
  - Printed ephemera, 1998-2003, undated (Box 4, Folder 49)